Guide to the Richard Bruce Nugent Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Audiovisual materials, 1983-1987; Series XIII; (1 box)
  - WBAI. Interview of Nugent and Others by David Jackson, c. 1984; 2 60-min Audio Cassettes
    Nugent, Jackson, Carl Yearwood (owner of Small's Paradise), Gordon Anderson (photographer and dancer), and Thomas Wirth
    - Nugent, David. Jackson, Gordon. Anderson, Tom Wirth. (1 of 2 audiocassettes), undated; 1 (Box 95 (Oversize), Item barcode 39002104614947)
    - Nugent, David. Jackson, Gordon. Anderson, Tom Wirth. (1 of 2 audiocassettes), undated; 1 (Box 95 (Oversize), Item barcode 39002104614954)
  - WLIB. Interview of Bruce Nugent by Judy Simmons, 1983 March 8; 1 (Box 95 (Oversize), Item barcode 39002104614939)
  - WPFW (Washington DC). "Air Check" Open Window. Interview of Bruce Nugent and Thomas Wirth by Ms. Gardner, 1983 October 18; 1 (Box 95 (Oversize), Item barcode 39002104614962)
  - "For Love of Bruce" by Jerry Perez, 1987; 1 (Box 95 (Oversize), Item barcode 39002104614970)
    Testimonial to RBN following his death by a man who was profoundly influenced by Nugent in his youth. Cf. Perez family correspondence; Nugent to Garber, Series 1, Box 6, Folder 12.
- Oversize materials and miscellaneous papers, 1928-2002; Series XIV; (4 boxes)
  - Nugent, Richard Henry, c 1910; 2 Pastel Drawings, 9" x 12" (Box 96 (Oversize))
    Very poor condition. Brittle, acidic paper, chipped and falling apart.
  - Dance Magazine, May 1928; 1 Issue (Box 96 (Oversize))
    Volume 10, Number 1 (May 1928). Contains "Harlem's Place in the Sun" by Wallace Thurman, illustrated with 6 drawings by Bruce Nugent. Front cover chipped and partially detached, contents fine.
  - McClendon, Rose, c 1929; Portrait Photograph by R. Frazier NY, 7.3" x 9.6", mounted (Box 96 (Oversize))
  - Nugent, Bruce with the Bust of Antinous, Hadrian's Favorite. Portrait Photograph by Carl Van Vechten, 16 Feb 1936; 1 Photograph, 10.75" x 13.75" (Box 96 (Oversize))
  - The Chronicle [of Higher Education] Review., 16 August 2002; 1 Issue (Box 96 (Oversize))
    Contains the article "Race, Ethnicity, and Queer Studies" by Robert Reid-Pharr. The article includes a review of Nugent's novel Gentleman Jigger.
  - Thompson, James W. "And The Oedipus Tale Should Prove, 26 Nov 1974; Broadside 15" x 9" (Box 96 (Oversize))
    Published by FIRE PUBLICATIONS, Inc. Printed on heavy stock. Inscribed "To Bruce, With deepest love -- James W. Thompson / 26 Nov. 74 / Heritage Hse. Stained.
  - Nugent, Bruce. Miscellaneous Handwritten Fragments, 7 Leaves 11" x 14" sketchbook pages (Box 96 (Oversize))
    Miscellaneous holograph fragments in Nugent's hand, including a 3-page segment of CIAO; draft of a letter to "Giovanni" [Rosmini?]
  - Pinckney, Martin. Portrait of Malcolm X, Halftone reproduction of a charcoal drawing 11" x 14" (Box 96 (Oversize))
    Inscribed "All the Best / Marty H. Pinckney.
  - Dali: April 14 to May 5, 1943, 1 Exhibition Catalog (Box 97 (Oversize))
    M. Knoedler Galleries, NYC. Inscribed "Bruce -- If I don't eat today its because of this here mad artist / as ever Chas [Charles Marr?]. Covers age-toned and stained. Small stains to the margins of a few pages; other the contents are very good.
  - Reade, Brian. Aubrey Beardsley, 1967; 1 Book (Box 97 (Oversize))
    New York: Bonanza Books. Boldly inscribed "to Bruce / who I love and is the best influence in my life / John Rosmini. Very good (+) in the dust jacket.
  - Barthe, 7/15/86; 3 Misc Items (Box 98)
    Press clippings & copies
  - Clippings, Several Items (Box 98)
    Various newspaper clippings
  - Cooper, Jerry (Correspondence), 1973-1977; 18 Letters (Box 98)
    Jerry Cooper was a gay American in Rome. His residence was a gay boarding house and gathering place.
  - Cuny, Waring (Correspondence), 1972; 1 Letter (Box 98)
  - Elethea, Abba, 1972, 1974; 2 Items (4 leaves) (Box 98)
    1. TL "Open Letter" to Paul Bremen (carbon copy) 2. Xerox copy of Springfield (Ohio) News-Sun article about Elethea
  - Dance Theatre of Harlem, 1972-1986; 4 Items (Box 98)
    Souvenir program for "Harlem Homecoming" (1972) and other publicity materials
  - Ellis, Evelyn, 1958; 1 Clipping (Box 98)
  - Forty Acres and a Mule, 1969 (Sept-Dec); 2 Issues (Box 98)
    Tabloid newspaper issued by the students in the Educational Program of the New York Urban League. Acidic paper, fragile but intact. Stained
  - Garber, Eric, 1981; Typed letter and several enclosures (Box 98)
    Enclosures include Xerox copies of articles from the Alternate and the Advocate and case studies from Henry's Sex Variants (1941).
  - Harlem Nightclubs, 1 Item (Box 98)
    Xerox copy of "Harlem Jazz Clubs Then and Now", a multipage narrative-catalog accompanying a record album.
  - Hatch Interview, 1982; 1 Item (Box 98)
    Typescript of Nugent's interview with Jim Hatch with corrections in Nugent's hand. The interview was published in the 1982 issue of the Hatch-Billops Collection's publication, Artists and Influences.
  - Hughes, Langston, 1962; 2 Newspaper Clippings (Box 98)
    1. Article about Hughes by Ted Posten 2. Column by Hughes about Nina Simone from the New York Post. Acidic newsprint.
  - Lewis Interview, 1974; 1 Items (Box 98)
    1. Typed notes by David Levering Lewis of his interview with Nugent "
  - Miscellaneous, 1 Item (Box 98)
    Schematic drawing for stage production
  - Music (Bessie Smith, Ethelbert Nevin), 2 Items (Box 98)
    Xerox copies
  - Nugent Cremation and Burial, 1987; Several Items (Box 98)
    Correspondence, bills, and other miscellaneous items
  - Nugent Will and Death Certificate, 1987; 3 Items (Box 98)
    Certified copy of Nugent's will; xerox copy of his death certificate; certification of Wirth as executor.
  - Porgy Program, 1929; 2 Items (Box 98)
    1. Broadside program for "Bird in Hand by John Drinkwater at the Schubert Theatre with an ad for Porgy. 2. Broadside program for Porgy at the Schubert Theatre (Week beginning Monday, December 9 [1929])
  - Schomburg Center, 1971, 1972; 2 Items (Box 98)
    Copies of correspondence
  - Studio, 118th Street, 1962; 1 Item (Box 98)
    Summons issued in connection with a mortgage foreclosure action against Nugent's landlady.
  - Theater (Negro Ensemble Company), 1984; 1 Item (Box 98)
    Fundraising brochure
  - Van Vechten, Carl, 1985; 3 Items (Box 98)
    Fine letterpress broadside of "My Favorite Authors" by CVV published by Bruce Kellner; lettered copy "U for Richard Bruce Nugent". Together with two envelopes.
  - Richard Bruce Nugent" by Thomas H. Wirth, 1985; 7 Leaves (Box 99)
    Holograph manuscript
  - Gay Rebel of the Harlem Renaissance, January 2002; 2 Items (Box 99)
    Proofs with holograph corrections by Wirth, together with a cover letter from Wirth.
  - Gay Rebel of the Harlem Renaissance, 2002; 1 Item (Box 99)
    Cover of the paperback edition.
  - Uranian Worlds: A Reader's Guide ot Alternative Sexuality in Science Fiction and Fantasy by Eric Garber and Lyn Paleo, August 1983; 1 Book (Box 99)
    Inscribed to Nugent by the editors. Condition: Poor. Badly chewed.
- Restricted papers, (3 boxes)
  - Papers restricted until January 1, 2037 (Box 102)
- Restricted fragile papers, (3 boxes)
  These materials from Series I, II, and III, along with other miscellaneous papers, are restricted due to damage from cat urine.
  - (Series I) Correspondence, 1982-1983; 9 Items (Box 103)
    Correspondence from: Garber, Eric (07/30/1982; 09/26/1983) Haynes, Olyve Jeter (10/1981) Kellner, Bruce (10/14/1982) Sanabria, Jesus (07/19/1982; 04/14/1983; 05/4/1983; 05/04/1983)
  - (Series I) D'Ambrosio / Zografos, Numerous Items (Box 103)
  - (Series II) HALF HIGH. -- "Epistle," pp. 1-3 & unpaginated; pp. 3-7. Fragment., 11 leaves (Box 103)
  - (Series II) HARLEM -- A CULTURAL CAPITOL by Bruce Nugent and James W. Thompson, 1 Item, 38 Leaves (Box 103)
    Outline for the publisher.
  - (Series II) HARLEM -- A CULTURAL CAPITOL by Bruce Nugent and James W. Thompson. Notes., Several leaves. (Box 103)
  - (Series II) HIGH JOHN THE CONQUEROR. Concept Outline for a Play., 3 Leaves. Badly stained. (Box 103)
  - (Series II) POEMS. "You Seek to Shame Me., 3 typewritten leaves and 1 holograph leaf. (Box 103)
    3 of the leaves acidic, tanned & fragile; 2 are chipped, 1 badly. Includes material not present in the version published in Gay Rebel.
  - CIAO (Series III), Numerous leaves (Box 103)
    Odd typescript pages.
  - (Series III). GENTLEMAN JIGGER, Chapter 13 ("Holy Ghost"). Notes., 2 leaves. Holograph. (Box 103)
  - (Series III) GENTLEMAN JIGGER, pp. 7-21., ca 1928; 15 leaves. Holograph in pencil. Corners stained. (Box 103)
    Ending of Book I. Omitted from the published version.
  - (Series III) SQUARE OF THE CIRCLE. Odd Manuscript Pages., Numerous leaves. (Box 104)
  - (Series III) SQUARE OF THE CIRCLE. Odd Manuscript Pages., Numerous leaves. (Box 104)
  - (Series III) SQUARE OF THE CIRCLE (?). Notes, 7 leaves, half page & smaller. Some stained (Box 104)
    Notes for a fictionalized version of Nugent's relationship with Louise Paul & others in the late 1930s. They roughly fit with the Square of the Circle, but may be for another, unwritten, novel.
  - (Series III) URANUS IN CANCER. Letters into Limbo, pp. {1, 3], 4-34, 36-41, ca 40 leaves. Tanned, stained paper. Some leaves fragile. (Box 104)
    Early manuscript.
  - (Series III) URANUS IN CANCER. Letters into Limbo, pp. 51-150., Numerous leaves. Carbon copy. Stained. Many pages missing. (Box 104)
  - Odd Manuscript Pages, Notes, Misc., Numerous leaves (Box 105)
  - Notes, Misc. (Box 105)
  - LANDSCAPES (Cartoons by R. Taylor with captions by Nugent., 4 photostats of the cartoons; 11 captions, handwritten on separate half-sheets of acidic, tanned paper. (Box 105)
  - ME, CANDIDO! -- Screenplay by Brad Kearny, pp. 1-33, ca 35 leaves. Carbon copy on onionskin. Stained. (Box 105)